Okay, בוקר טוב boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is דף ח.
daf chet. We pick up with where were we? אמר מר, amar
mar, it's about seven lines, six lines from the top, line starts
with the word נינהו, ninhu, and we are once again spending trying
to figure out, or continue you know this will be our focus
for a while, what exactly is the function of the קרבנות korbanot
that are brought on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and then on the
רגלים regalim and so on, we understand they're all related to טומאת
מקדש tumat mikdash and the impurity of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
the standard קרבן korban in the תורה Torah for עולה ויורד oleh
veyored where a changing where possible variable cost קרבן korban is for
ידיעה בתחילה וידיעה בסוף והעלם בינתים. yedi'ah bit'chilah veyedi'ah basof vehe'elam beintayim.
Person was aware at the outset they became טמא, tamei, they forgot,
they do something wrong, then they became aware again. And the different
various קרבנות korbanot on יום כיפור Yom Kippur that are brought inside
the קודש קדשים, kodesh kodashim, the מוסף, musaf, the רגלים regalim are
for different degrees of ידיעה yedi'ah without the ידיעה yedi'ah both endpoints.
So, and because of the emphasis there in the תורה Torah is
וכיפר על הקודש מטומאות בני ישראל ומפשעיהם לכל חטאתם. vechipper al hakodesh
mitumot bnei yisrael u'mipisheihem lechol chatotam. That it will atone for the
sanctuary on the impurities of בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So the first
thing that the גמרא Gemara has to do is reject the possibility
which in parenthesis could very well be understood as the פשט pshat
of the תורה, Torah, which is that the impurity here does not
mean the impurity like contact with you know dead animals and or
with various bodily fluids and those types of things, the standard things
we call טומאה, tumah, the things that prevent a person from eating
קרבנות korbanot or entering the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but that the
impurities here refer to impurities created by sin and that I've discussed
this before that according to many biblical commentators the פשט pshat of
the פסוקים psukim is, you know, that when you sin it it
impurifies the land, it creates impurity in the world, the impurity enters
into the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, the worst sins, the impurity goes
even deeper into the Holy of Holies and therefore once a year
the כהן גדול kohen gadol has to enter into that place which
has all where the impurities of all sort of clogged up the
you know the the you know the pipes as it were, clogged
up and maybe driven out to some degree or risk driving out
God's presence and cleansed it from the impurities, כיפר kipper naturally means
to atone but to cleanse. So the relationship of, you know, we
speak about my personal guilt, my personal need for atonement, I sinned,
I'm deserving of punishment, this is much more metaphysical and that's probably
a lot of the פשט pshat of what the עבודה avoda of
יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim is about is is that, you know, you
cleanse the מקדש mikdash from the sins generated from בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael which allows God השוכן אתם בתוך טומאותם. hashochen itam betoch tumotam.
Just think about that פסוק. pasuk. It does not mean because they
touched some dead carcass. God dwells among us in our impurity means
although we are by nature sinful God continues to dwell among us,
but what allows God to dwell among us in our impurity is
that once a year we, you know, we do a little house
cleaning and we make it more possible and we try to get
rid of that impurity. So that's the פשט pshat of the פסוקים
psukim and the גמרא Gemara to some degree really recognizes that or
at least raises it as a הוה אמינא. hava amina. Maybe טומאות
tumot means the טומאות tumot by עבודה זרה, avoda zara, גילוי עריות,
gilui arayot, and שפיכות דמים, shefichut damim, right,
the biggest sins for which the תורה Torah uses the word טומאה
tumah in relationship to them, and maybe that's what it's doing. But
the גמרא Gemara sort of like for technical reasons rejects all of
those possibilities. And you know ultimately because the פסוק pasuk says על
הקודש מטומאות בני ישראל, al hakodesh mitumot bnei yisrael, טומאה tumah that
relates to the קודש, kodesh, not טומאה tumah that relates to that's
at least what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says. You know, not טומאה
tumah that relates to or what do you call it, that relates
to the מטמא metamei the land or something. It's a much more
sort of narrowly defined טומאה. tumah. Or the other reason that it's
rejected is what's the other reason?
מטומאות ולא כל טומאות. mitumot v'lo kol tumot. A very technical reason,
which is interesting, which is like yeah, in principle it could be,
but it's only going to do some and not all. And why
and now we're going to decide why why so? Why why of
all the טומאות, tumot, why focus more on this issue of touching
like I'll call it dead animals type of טומאה? tumah? You know,
why is that the one? And again it's very it's ironic. The
whole big to-do of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, all of this עבודה,
avoda, whatever, I mean yes okay atonement for sin is the goat
that gets sent off. But you know but when we focus on
the עבודה avoda as like the central experience, you think about how
we דאווען daven מוסף musaf of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it's all
for this technical thing of somebody touched a dead animal and accidentally
entered into the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. I'm hoping to get off so easy, like if you
did עבודה זרה, avoda zara, you know, שפיכות דמים, shefichut damim, enter
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and you're all good?
Alright, I under- no not you're all good. Again, there's a difference
between the person's guilt and the person's deserving of punishment and how
sin generates impurity in the world and impurity in the מקדש mikdash
and makes it less possible for God or challenges the idea that
God can continue to dwell among us השוכן אתם בתוך טומאותם. hashochen
itam betoch tumotam. There's a very different focus here. Anyway, but let's
take a look. Now we have to figure out, okay, fine, some
of the טומאות tumot and not all, why are you picking these?
Why are you picking what I'll call the more technical טומאה? tumah?
אמר מר, Amar mar, so now picking up from that about seven
lines down on ח"א, chet aleph, אמר מר, Amar mar, יכול
על שלוש טומאות הללו יהא זה מכפר, yachol al shalosh tumot halalu
yehei zeh mechaper, maybe for these three, עבודה זרה גילוי עריות ושפיכות
דמים, avodah zarah, giluy arayot, ushfechut damim, תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, מטומאות
ולא כל טומאות, mitumot velo kol tumot, from the טומאות—we're tumot re-quoting
what we had yesterday—and not all the טומאות. tumot. Now why so
which ones do you pick? Why do you pick the ones of
touching, you know, dead animals for example? מה מצינו שחילק הכתוב מכלל
כל טומאות בטומאת מקדש וקדשיו אף כאן בטומאת מקדש וקדשיו. mah matzinu
shechilak hakatuv michlal kol tumot betumat mikdash vekodashav af kan betumat mikdash
vekodashav. The same way when it comes to a type of טומאה
tumah that prevents you from entering the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash or
eating קרבנות, korbanot, the תורה Torah gives it separate treatment elsewhere, so
here too on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, this is the one that
gets separate treatment, this is the one that the what do you
call it, that the atones for, that the קרבן korban of, you
know, the שעיר se'ir that's brought, the קרבנות korbanot that are brought
inside the קודש הקודשים Kodesh HaKodashim or the מוסף, Musaf, these are
the ones that it atones for are the ones that get separate
treatment elsewhere. So where's this separate treatment that is given to טומאת
מקדש וקדשיו? tumat mikdash vekodashav?
Okay,
דברי רבי יהודה, divrei Rabbi Yehuda, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says. מאי חילק, mai chilek, you know, what does it mean that
it's given separate treatment? דמייתי עולה ויורד, demayti oleh veyored, that when
somebody does this, touches a dead animal for example, dead body, and
then eats a קרבן korban or enters the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
if he has the requisite ידיעה, yedi'ah, ידיעה yedi'ah in the beginning,
ידיעה yedi'ah in the end, forgetting in between, he brings a קרבן,
korban, but it's a קרבן korban of variable cost, it is עולה
ויורד, oleh veyored, okay, depending on his ability to afford it. So
therefore it gives, it makes it easy for the, a little bit
easier than normal for the person to atone for. Okay, you don't
have to, so because it makes, it wants you to get atonement,
allows a sliding scale based on your ability to afford, we're going
to assume here on יום כיפור Yom Kippur as well, if the
תורה Torah wants to cleanse the טומאה tumah or deal with the
sin of the טומאה, tumah, it wants to do it in a
case where we've already seen that the תורה Torah is trying to
make it a little bit easier to address this sin. So the
same way we see that here by the עולה ויורד, oleh veyored,
the sliding scale, we're going to assume that is the טומאה tumah
that is being addressed on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, so דמייתי
עולה ויורד. demayti oleh veyored. So אימא עבודה זרה, eima avodah zarah,
well, maybe the תורה Torah wants us to get rid of the
sin of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. ומאי חילק, umai chilek, and where
would I see that the תורה Torah gave special treatment to
עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? דמייתי שעירה ולא כשבה, demayti se'irah velo kishbah,
because you bring a goat as opposed to a sheep. Normally, well,
kind of easier because I've already hinted to that difference. So anyway
normally by a normal sin you can bring either a goat or
a sheep, female goat or sheep, and by עבודה זרה avodah zarah
only a goat. אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, אנן חילק להקל
קאמינא והאי חילק להחמיר. anan chilek lehakel ka'amina vehai chilek lehachmir. It's
not just separate treatment, I already sort of anticipate read in the
later גמרא, Gemara, it's not just that it treats it separately, it
treats separately in a lenient way. עולה ויורד, oleh veyored, the תורה
Torah is being lenient, it's making it easier to bring the קרבן
korban because it's making it a sliding scale. So therefore if the
תורה Torah wants to make it easier to get atonement, I'll say
it wants to get you atonement on יום כיפור Yom Kippur as
well, it's trying to make it easier to get atonement for this.
Whereas by עבודה זרה avodah zarah it's making it harder to get
atonement. I mean it's not so hard to bring a goat, whatever,
but it limits your options. I'd rather be able to bring a
goat or a sheep rather than just have to bring a goat.
So the fact, we are looking for a case that we can
see that the תורה Torah is trying to make it easier on
you. That we have by טומאת מקדש, tumat mikdash, we don't have
by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא יולדת,
ve'eima yoledet, how about a woman who gives childbirth? Okay, and
she has to bring a קרבן, korban, and the קרבן korban that
a woman gives after childbirth is an עולה ויורד, oleh veyored, it's
similarly just like this טומאת מקדש, tumat mikdash, it's variable, a sliding
scale what type of קרבן korban she brings. So what's the הוה
אמינא hava amina though? The הוה אמינא hava amina רש"י Rashi says
is very interesting. רש"י Rashi says the הוה אמינא hava amina is
a woman had birth before יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, she hasn't gotten
around to bringing her קרבן, korban, comes יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and
then after יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, great, I don't have to bring
my קרבן korban because it was מכפר, mechaper, you know, talk about
טומאות בני ישראל, tumot benei Yisrael, there's a טומאה, tumah, the טומאה
tumah of יולדת, yoledet, okay, and I don't have to bring my
קרבן. korban. תוספות Tosafot is a little bothered because the גמרא Gemara
sort of assumes that if you have a clear obligation of a
קרבן, korban, the קרבן korban of יום כיפור Yom Kippur isn't going
to get you off the hook. So תוספות Tosafot says maybe it
means a woman who is not sure whether she miscarried before or
after 40 days, because a miscarriage you'd also bring a קרבן, korban,
but only after 40 days after conception. So in some issue maybe
where there's a doubt or whatever the case might be, if יום
כיפור Yom Kippur rolls around, that is the קרבן korban for this
woman and therefore she doesn't bring the קרבן korban after that. Maybe
that's what it's showing that it really works one minute with the
idea of טומאות בני ישראל tumot benei Yisrael and that's חילק הכתוב.
chilak hakatuv.
So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא יולדת ve'eima yoledet דחילק דמייתי עולה
ויורד, dechilek demayti oleh veyored, you bring a sliding scale קרבן. korban.
אמר רבי אושעיא, Amar Rabbi Oshaya, לכל חטאתם, lechol chatotam, it says
that it's מכפר mechaper from טומאות בני ישראל לכל חטאתם. mitumot benei
Yisrael lechol chatotam. It has to have two elements: טומאה tumah and
sin. Okay, so you know עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, גילוי עריות, gilui
arayot, שפיכות דמים, shefichut damim, it definitely has sin and טומאה tumah
we discussed. There's also an idea of טומאה tumah in general by
sin. טומאת מקדש tum'at mikdash has טומאה tumah and has sin. You
ate a קרבן korban when you shouldn't have eaten it. But here
it doesn't have the sin component. לכל חטאותם ולא לכל טומאותם, l'chol
chatotam v'lo l'chol tumotam, not something that's just טומאה, tumah, something that
is טומאה tumah and sin. So when a woman brings a קרבן
korban for childbirth, there's no sin involved. She's just bringing it to
address the טומאה tumah element. So therefore that is not what the
קרבן korban on יום כיפור Yom Kippur is about. The קרבן korban
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur has to have a dimension of sin.
So now the גמרא Gemara says ולרבי שמעון בר יוחאי דאמר יולדת
נמי חוטאת היא מאי איכא למימר? v'lirabbi Shimon bar Yochai d'amar yoledet
nami choteit hi mai ika l'meimar? But wait, רבי שמעון בר יוחאי
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai says the reason a woman who has a
child brings a קרבן korban and it's a קרבן חטאת korban chatat
is because she is considered to some degree to be a sinner.
Why is she a sinner? Because the גמרא Gemara says, well רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says because we assume that when she's in the
middle of giving birth and suffering the child pains, she takes an
oath which is "I am never going to have sex with my
husband ever again, if this is what it means." So therefore, because
of that, she needs some atonement. Okay, so according to him, there
is an element of sin here. So the גמרא Gemara says רבי
שמעון לטעמיה דאמר מכמוהו הוא מוכרח. Rabbi Shimon l'taimei d'amar mikmohu hu
muchrach. Okay, but remember, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that the way
we know the קרבן korban of יום כיפור Yom Kippur is about
טומאת מקדש tum'at mikdash is because it says וכיפר על הקודש מטומאות
בני ישראל. v'chiper al hakodesh mitumot b'nei Yisrael.
So he doesn't say it's חילק. chilek. He doesn't say just something
that has separate treatment. If it had separate treatment, maybe he would
have picked יולדת. yoledet. He says it's already by context it's clear
we're talking about specifically טומאת מקדש. tum'at mikdash. But according to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says we're just looking for something that's given
separate treatment, so he would say, well the reason we didn't turn
to יולדת yoledet is יולדת yoledet is only about טומאה tumah and
it's not about טומאה tumah and sin and we need something that's
both about טומאה tumah and sin. I just want to say something
about a יולדת yoledet and the חטאת, chatat, and that again goes
to this idea of what we think a חטאת chatat is about,
okay? And this goes back again central to the idea of יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. Like I said, וכיפר על הקודש v'chiper al hakodesh
means to cleanse, doesn't just mean to atone. If you think about
it as getting the טומאה tumah out of the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. Similarly, the word of חטאת, chatat, which we normally translate as
sin, right, לחטא lechatei could also mean essentially, it could mean to
sprinkle, but it could mean also to cleanse, okay? And it's not
really about sin. So why does a יולדת yoledet bring a חטאת?
chatat? It is not because she did some sin. There are places
where somebody brings a חטאת chatat as the end of a טהרה
tahara process. At the end of a process of going from impurity
to purity. And again that shows, right, מצורע, metzora, other cases. And
again that shows that, you know, a central theme here that is
mostly being sort of bracketed by the גמרא, Gemara, a little bit
being acknowledged by עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, גילוי עריות, gilui arayot, שפיכות
דמים, shefichut damim, etc., but a central theme here about the role
of a חטאת chatat in general, forget יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. I
go ahead and I sin and accidentally I break שבת, Shabbat, I
bring a חטאת. chatat. So we normally think it's a way of
God forgiving me, okay? But actually to some degree, maybe it's some
of it, but to some degree it's because my violation maybe didn't
create terrible טומאה tumah that needs to be dealt with on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur because it wasn't במזיד b'meizid and whatever, but it
created a certain amount of טומאה tumah in the world and a
certain amount of rupture, and now my חטאת chatat has to come
clean up the mess that I made. Okay? It's not just, it's
not as much about me, right? It's very funny when we think
about sin, right, it's we very much think about like my sin,
what do I need to do to get this punishment and burden
and, you know, stain off of me, okay? But you know, how
would, what would if we thought about it differently? I sinned and
therefore first of all if it's בין אדם לחבירו, bein adam l'chavero,
what do I have to do? If we started not by focusing,
normally we say I have to make up with you if I
want, if I want to be forgiven. What if we took the
I want to be forgiven out of the equation altogether? I hurt
you, my obligation is to fix the hurt that I did to
you. I went ahead and I did a sin in the world,
I broke שבת, Shabbat, I have to fix that violation that I
did in the world. So the way I fix that violation, if
it's religious and not interpersonal, right, is I bring a חטאת chatat
if it was בשוגג, b'shogeg, right? So that sort of allows that
to be fixed. So that's a real important shift in thinking in
general in the Torah, what is sin about? Is it about focus
about me and my guilt and my punishment, or does it focus
on the rupture and what I've done wrong in the world and
how, what therefore is a קרבן korban of that? And is a
קרבן korban about sort of fixing that and cleaning that? One example
of this is, to show that it might have nothing to do
or not require an element of guilt or fault, is that the
גמרא Gemara says
if you have a תינוק שנשבה לבין הגוים, tinok shenishba l'vein hagoyim,
a child was taken captive, he was brought up, he never knew
that he was Jewish in his life, he was raised in China
all his life, he was, you know, he thought he was Chinese,
he never heard of Jews at all or whatever, 20 years he
lived. doing work on Saturday, and then he one day decided to
research his birth parents and he found out that he was Jewish,
okay, and there happens to be a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. How
many קרבנות Korbanos does he have to bring? So the גמרא Gemara
says well he doesn't have to bring one for every מלאכה melacha
and he doesn't have to bring one for every שבת, Shabbos, I
mean the poor kid, the guy never knew he was Jewish. But
he does have to bring one קרבן. Korban. Why does he have
to bring one קרבן? Korban? He's completely blameless. So even you could
be completely blameless and still have to bring a קרבן Korban because
still at the end of the day, like you sort of like
you broke it, you fix it, I don't care if it wasn't
your fault, okay? And that's a concept of what קרבן Korban does,
right? So anyway, it's so important to acknowledge that and therefore also
a חטאת Chatas by a woman who's childbirth or other types of
people that are טמא, tamei, the reason of a חטאת Chatas does
not have to point you back to an idea of sin. The
reason of חטאת Chatas is part of what a חטאת Chatas does
is it cleanses, it could cleanse some sin that was created in
the world, and it could cleanse a טומאה tuma of a person.
But the very much much more in terms of cleansing and impurity
and fixing something out there rather than sin and atoning and forgiving,
you know, my sin. That's a very different way, which is really
more like a post מקדש Mikdash way of thinking about it, and
not so much in terms of how they were functioning, you know,
in the from in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash context, yes.
I want to get back to something you said earlier. It seems
to me that we're having somewhat of a dichotomy because when we're
still talking about the עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
שפיכות דמים, shfichus damim, and גילוי עריות giluy arayos and saying well
what? So then you know you bring some date off like no,
it's to cleanse the מקדש, Mikdash, but then you were saying regarding
the יולדת yoledes that it would get it off?
He doesn't have anything to get off from, it's just טומאה. tuma.
But it cleanses טומאה.
tuma. It doesn't- if you're a sinner we have to deal with
that separately. And if you sinned במזיד b'meizid we'll punish you with
the proper punishment, okay? And if you sinned בשוגג, bishogeg, then maybe
God will forgive you if you clean up the mess, okay? But
it's a very- but it's the you know- but but yeah, so
yeah.
I just think Hebrew is more helpful if you translate it to
non-Jewish terms, like terms around the sin is not helpful. But לחטוא
lachto like to miss the mark, right, and לקרוב likrov to be
close again. So I think more in those terms kind of helps
me wrap my head around it.
Right, so often right that's true, קרבן Korban is meant as לקרוב
likarov to get close to God, and לחטוא, lachto, the word is
החטאה hachtaa about sin or about error, right, I think those are
related, but again I think that what I'm trying to also focus
on is something a little more external and metaphysical, sort of world
cosmic as it were. But yes, that's also very important too, right?
When we talk about sacrifice and sin as opposed to like, you
know, error and rupture and drawing close and so on, absolutely. Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, fine.
אימא מצורע, Eima metzora, how about a מצורע? metzora? And a מצורע
metzora also brings an עולה ויורד, olah v'yored, so maybe it's helping
for the טומאה tuma of a מצורע, metzora, maybe that's what this
קרבן Korban of יום כיפור Yom Kippur does. Obviously it's going to
be the same answer as a יולדת. yoledes. So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר רב הושעיא לכל חטאתם ולא לכל טומאותם. Amar Rav Oshaya
l'chol chatosam v'lo l'chol tumosam.
And those that say that צרעת tzaraas is because of a sin?
Well we're going to get there. Okay so no, מצורע metzora
the קרבן Korban of a מצורע metzora is only about about impurity,
there's not an element of sin, and therefore the יום כיפור Yom
Kippur קרבן Korban is not relevant to that. יום כיפור Yom Kippur
קרבן Korban means both. So the גמרא Gemara says ורבי שמואל בר
נחמני דאמר אמר רבי יונתן על שבעה דברים נגעים באין v'Rabbi Shmuel
bar Nachmani de'amar Amar Rabbi Yonatan al shiva devarim negaim ba'in that
leprosy comes for seven types of sin. We all know the לשון
הרע, lashon hara, you can go take a look at the list
to find out what else. Anyway, there's an element of sin here
as well. So why don't we say the יום כיפור Yom Kippur
קרבן Korban cleanses the מצורע metzora who is the you know the
מצורע metzora who is for the- who is part of the קרבן
Korban for the cleansing of the מצורע metzora which also has an
element of sin? Let's say that's what the יום כיפור Yom Kippur
קרבן Korban is about. So the גמרא Gemara says התם נגעי דאכפר
ליה. Hasam negaie d'achpar leih. My mistake, it's
התם. Hasam. So there, no no no, you missed- you got it
wrong. Yes there's a sin, but the the atonement for the sin
came through the צרעת. tzaraas. The צרעת, tzaraas, the suffering of the
צרעת, tzaraas, that was his atonement. When it's time to bring the
קרבן, Korban, that just functions at dealing with the טומאה tuma level.
The קרבן Korban is not dealing with the sin level. הקרבן לאשתרויי
בקהל. hakorban l'ishtruye bikhal. The קרבן Korban is now to allow him
to come back to the ציבור. tzibur. לאשתרויי בקהל L'ishtruye bikhal is
probably the wrong phrase, that's more relevant for something else like a
גר. geir. If you look at the side, the better גרסא girsa
is לאשתרויי בקדשים. l'ishtruye b'kodashim. To allow him to eat? Right, exactly.
So by the time he gets around to the קרבן, Korban, the
צרעת tzaraas was his sin thing. By the time it's time for
the קרבן, Korban, that's just about טומאה, tuma, and the קרבן Korban
of יום כיפור Yom Kippur has to also be about sin.
ואימא נזיר טמא, v'eima nazir tamei, how about a נזיר טמא nazir
tamei who brings a קרבן, Korban, okay, ודחיליק v'dichlik
now and that also is a similar way of singling out... out
because it is a lot not an expensive חטאת, Chatas, it's a
חטאת Chatas of birds. דחליק דמייתי תורים ובני יונה Dechileik demaisei torim
uvenei yonah brings pigeons and turtledoves, so it's a bird קרבן Korban
חטאת, Chatas, it's a way the תורה's Torah making it easier to
bring a חטאת. Chatas. So maybe that's what the קרבן Korban of
יום כיפור Yom Kippur is because we're looking for an example of
an easy חטאת. Chatas. So why did you focus on מקדש וקדשיו?
Mikdash Vekodashav? How about the נזיר טמא? Nazir Tamei? So the גמרא's
Gemara going to have the exact same answer. אמר רב הושעיא, Amar
Rav Hoshaya, לכל חטאתם Lechol chatosam ולא לכל טומאותם. Velo lechol tumosam.
Again, exactly- it's just- yeah, it's just a טומאה Tumah issue, it's
not a sin issue. We need something that's a sin that's a
טומאה Tumah and a sin issue. So the גמרא Gemara says ואלעזר
הקפר Ve'Elazar Hakappar דאמר De'amar נזיר Nazir נמי Nami חוטא Chotei הוא
Hu מאי איכא למימר? Mai ika lemeimar? But one minute, אלעזר הקפר
Elazar Hakappar says a נזיר Nazir is a sinner. Why is a
נזיר Nazir a sinner? Because שצער עצמו מן היין, Sheteiar atzmo min
hayayin, he denied himself the pleasure of wine. Okay, because it says
אשר חטא על הנפש. Asher chata al hanefesh. So therefore it is
about sin. Now, of course the funny thing is then why is
only a נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei bringing the קרבן? Korban? Every נזיר
Nazir should bring a similar קרבן Korban if it's about sin. Not
this קרבן, Korban, not this חטאת Chatas that we're explaining. Where the
תורה Torah says אשר חטא על הנפש, Asher chata al hanefesh, which
is where he says that you sinned against what soul, against your
own soul, by denying yourself the pleasures of wine and so on,
okay, that's about a נזיר טמא. Nazir Tamei. So תוספות Tosafot says,
well, okay, because the נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei extended it, maybe he
wanted to do it once, it serves some purpose, right, and maybe
that counterbalances whatever negative there is in the self-denial of wine. But
if you allowed yourself now to become טמא, Tamei, and it's true
you can't always prevent it or whatever, but now it's being extended
beyond some justifiable purpose. So according to him, there's also a- there's
also a sin element, so maybe that's what the יום כיפור Yom
Kippur thing will do- will function in that term.
And נזיר לעולם, Nazir le'olam, would you still bring the same קרבן
Korban for being טמא Tamei then?
Yeah, that's true, yeah, what can I tell you. Anyway, so מאי
Mai איכא Ika למימר? Lemeimar? סבר לה כרבי שמעון Savar lah keRabbi
Shimon דאמר De'amar ממקומו הוא מוכרע. Mimkomo hu muchra. All right, fine,
according to that, you're right, we could have maybe landed on something
else, on נזיר טמא, Nazir Tamei, but if that's where you're holding,
then you could come to the same conclusion by holding like רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, who says you learn it from context. Okay, so
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda approach is, yes, there's a lot of טומאות
Tumos we could have settled on, but the תורה Torah says מטומאת
בני ישראל Mitumot benei Yisrael and we're going to pick the one
טומאה Tumah that the תורה Torah gave special lenient treatment. And that
we've identified as טומאת מקדש וקדשיו Tumat mikdash vekodashav by being טמא
Tamei and eating קרבנות. Korbanos. Maybe you could have figured out something
else that both had a טומאה Tumah and a חטא Cheit element
to it. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara eliminated most of those possibilities.
If you feel that there was other- some other live possibility there,
in the end you always have רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon to go
back to, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that you learn it
out immediately from context. Because it says וכיפר על הקודש מטומאות בני
ישראל. Vechiper al hakodesh mitumot benei Yisrael.
It's a type of טומאה Tumah that directly relates to the מקדש,
Mikdash, and that's the טומאה Tumah that is being addressed by the
יום כיפור Yom Kippur קרבן. Korban. So now the גמרא Gemara looks
at רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אמר מר רבי שמעון אומר ממקומו הוא
מוכרע. Amar mar Rabbi Shimon omer mimkomo hu muchra. הרי הוא אומר
וכיפר על הקודש מטומאות בני ישראל. Harei hu omer vechiper al hakodesh
mitumot benei Yisrael. מטומאות של קודש, Mitumot shel kodesh, the type of-
of טומאה Tumah that impacts directly the מקדש Mikdash itself when you
are טמא Tamei and enter into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So
שפיר קאמר רבי שמעון. Shapir ka'amar Rabbi Shimon. Yeah, that's a pretty
darn good point. I mean, it's right there in the פסוק. Pasuk.
Why do you have to go look for something- for some other
reason to say that's what it means?
So שפיר קאמר רבי שמעון. Shapir ka'amar Rabbi Shimon. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda אמר לך, Amar lach, he'll say back to you, ההוא מיבעי
ליה כי היכי דעביד לפני ולפנים הכי נמי עביד בהיכל. Hahu mibaei
leih ki heichi de'avid lifnai velifnim hachi nami avid baheichal. Because
no, what it's telling us is like this: the תורה Torah says
that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol goes with the blood of the
פר Par and the blood of the שעיר Seir into the Holy
of Holies, right, and it says- you know, and it says what
it says- yeah, what's the פסוק? Pasuk?
Ah,
it's like this. והזה אותו על הכפורת ולפני הכפורת. Vehizah oso al
hakaporet velifnei hakaporet. So he says he takes the blood of the
שעיר, Seir, he sprinkles it on the- you know- cover of the-
lid I mean- of the- of the ארון Aron and in front
of it. וכיפר על הקודש מטומאות בני ישראל ומפשעיהם לכל חטאתם וכן
יעשה לאוהל מועד השוכן איתם בתוך טומאותם. Vechiper al hakodesh mitumot benei
Yisrael umipisheihem lechol chatosam vechen ya'aseh leohel moed hashochein itam besoch tumosam.
Just like I did he did here for the Holy of Holies,
okay, here he is, he's like sprinkling here, whatever, here's the ארון
Aron or whatever, he's sprinkling the blood here, okay, one and seven
etc. And then it says וכיפר על הקודש. Vechiper al hakodesh. So
this is קודש קדשים Kodesh Kadashim and this is קודש. Kodesh. So
he comes- so he comes out here after he does the stuff
in there and he does a similar sprink- sprink- sprinkling on the
פרוכת Paroches and that cleanses the קודש. Kodesh. This cleanses the קודש
קדשים, Kodesh Kadashim, this cleanses the קודש. Kodesh. So that's וכיפר Vechiper
על Al על הקודש *al hakodesh*
he says is not coming to tell you מטומאות *mi'tumaos*. So רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* would say, you, I you רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*
say טומאת קודש *tumas kodesh*, it's telling you it's about the somebody
טמא tamei *tamei* who enters the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. I say
it has to tell me this, this is not the sin it's
atoning for. This is the act of atonement. He is being atoning
the same way he atoned on the קודש קודשים *Kodesh Kadashim*, he's
doing an act of sprinkling on the קודש *Kodesh*. For,
yes, because the טומאה *tuma* could mean, I don't know, גילוי עריות
ושפיכות דמים *gilui arayos v'shfichus damim*. It's not טומאה *tuma* of the
קודש *Kodesh*, it's כיפר על הקודש *kipper al hakodesh*. He does the
sprinkling on the you know פרוכת *paroches* of the of the קודש
*Kodesh*. The טומאות *tumaos* maybe for all we know is עבודה זרה
וגילוי עריות ושפיכות דמים *avoda zara v'gilui arayos v'shfichus damim*. It's not
טומאה *tuma* of the קודש *Kodesh*, it's a sprinkling on the קודש
*Kodesh*. That's what it's telling me, and that's why I couldn't just
learn it out from those words itself.
Why did he eliminate גילוי עריות *gilui arayos*?
Whatever, I mean, that's why he needed another basis. That's why he
needed to say מטומאות ולא כל טומאות *mi'tumaos v'lo kol tumaos*. Okay,
he could not learn it out מן כמוהו *min k'mohu*. He could
not learn it out from the words קודש טומאות *kodesh tumaos* because
he says no, וכיפר על הקודש *v'chipper al hakodesh* is not telling
you a טומאה *tuma* that affects the קודש *Kodesh*. He learns it,
you know, I'm going to learn back from the מ *mem*, but
the word קודש *kodesh* here is just saying that the act of
atonement is done on the קודש *Kodesh*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says כהיכי דעביד לפני ולפנים הכי נמי עביד בהיכל *k'heichi d'avid lifnai
v'lifnim hachinam avid baheichal*. That's what the word קודש *Kodesh* is telling
you. It's not telling you that it's a טומאה *tuma* of the
קודש *Kodesh*. So רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, no, ההוא מכן יעשה נפק
*hahu m'ken yaaseh nafak*. That's explicit because the פסוק posuk *pasuk* goes
on to say וכן יעשה לאהל מועד השוכן אתם בתוך טומאתם *v'chen
yaaseh l'ohel moed hashochen itam b'toch tumosam*. The end of the פסוק
posuk *pasuk* says do the same thing on the אהל מועד *Ohel
Moed*.
So right, so therefore, okay, so
it says right וכן יעשה
לאהל
מועד
*v'chen
yaaseh l'ohel moed*. So comes רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* and he says
וכן יעשה לאהל מועד *v'chen yaaseh l'ohel moed* is telling you you
do the sprinkling. And therefore out there, and therefore וכיפר על הקודש
מטומאות al hakodesh mitumot *v'chipper al hakodesh
mi'tumaos* is not telling you what act you're doing, that's this. This
is telling you what it's atoning for. It's atoning for טומאת קודש
*tumas kodesh*. That's what רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says. This is telling
you you do the act of sprinkling and this is telling you
it's atoning for the טומאה *tuma* of the קודש *Kodesh*. And I
don't need to go say חילק הכתוב *chileik hakatuv*. It's right there
in the פסוק posuk *pasuk*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* would say no, אם
מהי הוה אמינא נייתי פר ושעיר אחרינא ונעביד *im mehi havi amina
naisei par v'sa'ir achrinei v'naavid*. קמשמע לן *k'mashma lan*. No, he says
if I just had וכן יעשה *v'chen yaaseh*, I would have thought
what it means is you bring a goat and a cow and
you do this blood inside, and now you have to do the
same thing outside, not with the same blood, but go slaughter another
goat and another cow. וכן יעשה *v'chen yaaseh* sounds like you do
the whole thing over again. Okay, if all I had was וכן
יעשה *v'chen yaaseh*, I would have thought I had to slaughter a
whole new cow and a whole new goat. So the it's the
combination of the two. This says do a similar thing, but by
repeating וכיפר על הקודש *v'chipper al hakodesh* as a continuation of what
you did back here, that's telling me don't bring another goat and
a cow, just use the same blood and do it out here.
So for רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* this entire thing is needed to
tell me do this. Okay, and therefore he has to learn out
what type of sin we're talking about from the extra from the
מטומאות *mi'tumaos* and the חילק הכתוב *chileik hakatuv*. Okay, I couldn't tell
that's רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. Whereas רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* would say
this part of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* tells me you do the
act and this part of the פסוק *pasuk* tells me the sin
is a sin of טומאת קודש *tumas kodesh*. All right, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, אמר מר Amar mar, *amar
mar*, fine, so that's where רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* learns it out
from and why רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* thought you couldn't just learn
it out from context. You needed the whole פסוק *pasuk* to tell
me to do the act, again with the same blood. אמר מר
יכול יהא כל חטאת chatat, שבקודש יהא זה מכפר mechaper תלמוד לומר
מפשעיהם לכל חטאתם Talmud lomar mipisheihem l'chol chatatam. *amar mar yachol yeha
kol chatas shebakodesh yeha ze m'chaper talmud lomar mipesheihem l'chol chatosam*. Okay,
so now we've got it, whether you're רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* or
whether you're רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, you say that this this works
on טומאת קודש *tumas kodesh*. But now we have to figure out
which sins of טומאת קודש *tumas kodesh*. So remember, we have the
following sins. I don't know what happened to my other markers. Anyway,
we have the following sins. We have ידיעה בתחילה
ובסוף
yedia bitchila
u'vesof, *yedia
batichla u'v'sof* and that is עולה ויורד oleh v'yored. *oleh v'yored*,
right?
All right, we'll do it like this, because that's how we're going
to do it. תחילה *techila*,
סוף
*sof*. is going to work?
Yeah, but that first one has the middle category like העלם באמצע.
helem ba'emtza.
No, I know, I know it's העלם helem, באמצע.
Trying to figure out, no, no, the three have to sit in
the chart and the first one is hard to draw.
Yeah, but, yeah, hold on, hold on. If it's בדיעבד, b'diavad, let
me just see. If it's
ידיעה בתחילה yedia bitchila ובסוף,
okay, yeah, this is how we'll do it right. Okay, עולה ויורד.
oleh v'yored.
Okay. בתחילה בתחילה בסוף tchila bitchila besof is an עולה ויורד. oleh
v'yored, So then we have four other possibilities.
Only there's העלם, helem, right?
Yeah, yeah, there's העלם, helem. that's I'm taking for granted there's an
העלם. Okay. So there's neither ידיעה בתחילה yedia bitchila or בסוף, besof,
right? That's total four possibilities, right? Okay. ידיעה yedia right, ידיעה
בתחילה ולא בסוף, yedia bitchila v'lo besof, and you right, okay.
Right? Those are four
possibilities, right?
Everybody get that? Okay. So this is עולה ויורד, what we wind
up saying is is that this is the, you know, the יום
כיפור בפנים, Yom Kippur bifnim, right? So... right? What's done inside the
קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. This is יום כיפור המוסף Yom Kippur hamusaf
that's done בחוץ, bachutz, and this is רגלים Regalim and ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh.
Okay? That's basically our breakdown. So now we learned because of, you
know, על הקודש
מטומאות that יום כיפור Yom Kippur is מכפר mechaper for טומאת מקדש.
tumat mikdash. How do we know which one of these it's מכפר
mechaper for? That's the next thing the גמרא Gemara wants to know.
I know it's מכפר mechaper for טומאת מקדש, tumat mikdash, but which
one of these is it מכפר mechaper for? So let's take a
look. Okay, so it says the following. It says, okay, so אמר
מר, יכול על טומאה שבקדש יהא זה מכפר מכל טומאה, Yachol al
tumah she'bakodesh yeheh zeh mechaper mikol tumah,
maybe it works for the whole list. Okay. תלמוד לומר מפשעיהם mipisheihem,
לכל חטאתם. lechol chatotam, From...
so it says from the sins of all of their... what do
you call it? Of all their iniquities of all their sins. So
it says the same way פשע pesha is a willful sin and
there's no קרבן, korban, it can only atone for something that you're
not... that you're not bringing a קרבן korban for. Okay, the comparison
of חטאת, chatat, which is unintentional, to פשע, pesha, which is willful,
is willful doesn't have a קרבן, korban, so ביום כיפור, be'Yom Kippur,
because it says מפשעיהם, it cannot be this because this you already
bring a קרבן korban for. So we cannot be talking about the
first one. So it can only possibly be one of these three
because these are things that you are not bringing a קרבן korban
for and therefore that could be what יום כיפור Yom Kippur works
for. Okay, but which one of those three? מאי
מיהו? Mai mihu? So what's a type of a something that you
would not already bring a קרבן korban for? יש בה ידיעה בתחילה
ואין בה ידיעה בסוף. yesh bah yedia bitchila v'ein bah yedia besof.
I'm sorry, which is the one you are bringing a קרבן korban
for? יש בה ידיעה בתחילה ויש בה ידיעה בסוף. yesh bah yedia
bitchila v'yesh bah yedia besof. So... so that's the one, so we
know that that's not included because פשעיהם pisheihem says it's something that
you're not already bringing a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara says
you don't need the word פשעיהם pisheihem to tell you that. Of
course if you're already bringing a קרבן korban for, you're not going
to do the יום כיפור Yom Kippur קרבן, korban, right? Why would
יום כיפור Yom Kippur קרבן korban do it? Bring your own lousy
קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara. says האי בר קרבן הוא. hai
bar korban hu. So of course why do you need פשעיהם pisheihem
to exclude that if you're obligated in the קרבן, korban, you're obviously
not doing the יום כיפור Yom Kippur קרבן. korban. No, well, צריכא
דאיתידע ליה סמוך לשקיעת החמה. Tzricha d'ityada leh samuch l'shkiat hachama. No,
what happened was was right a minute before it was sunset on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right before יום כיפור Yom Kippur began, you
realized, oh my God, I just did this sin of טומאת מקדש,
tumat mikdash, I've got to bring a קרבן korban and so on.
So in that scenario, you didn't have a chance to bring it
yourself because then it became יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So maybe in
that scenario יום כיפור Yom Kippur would... this קרבן korban would get
you out of your קרבן. korban. You got the case? You realized
a minute before יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, maybe it would get you
out. So סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, I would say דמייתי
ניכפר ליה, d'maiti nichper leh, and maybe or maybe even it wouldn't
get you out of it, maybe until יום כיפור Yom Kippur is
over, this קרבן korban protects you, suspends the punishment until you get
a chance to bring it yourself. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan
that no, the פשעיהם pisheihem tells you even if you didn't get
a chance to bring this, if you're obligated in your own קרבן,
korban, don't come looking to us. That's not the responsibility of the
יום כיפור Yom Kippur קרבן. korban. That has nothing to do with
this. יום כיפור Yom Kippur קרבן korban is limited to things that
you're not... that you're not obligated in a קרבן. korban. So it's
one of these three. But how are we going now limit it
to this first one? We're talking here about the blood that's done
inside the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
Okay, so now we continue. אמר מר מניין שיש בה ידיעה בתחילה
ואין בה ידיעה בסוף ששעיר זה תולה. Amar mar minayin sheyesh bah
yedia bitchila v'ein bah yedia besof she'sa'ir zeh toleh. How do you
know... תולה? toleh? How do you know that it works for this
one? There's ידיעה בתחילה yedi'ah batchilah and not ידיעה בסוף. yedia besof.
How do we know this becomes the one that it focuses on?
So מניין... minayin... So מנין, minayin, so מאי קשיא ליה? mai kashya
lei? What's the difficulty? You've already excluded the case of ידיעה בתחילה
וסוף. yedi'ah batchilah basof. No, הכי קא קשיא ליה, hachi ka kashya
lei, this is what's bothering it. השתא דאמרת חטאים דומיא דפשעים, Hashta
de'amart chata'im dumya depesha'im, you say it has to be a
sin like a willful sin. It has to be one that doesn't
have a קרבן korban associated with it already. מה פשעים דלא בני
קרבן אף חטאים נמי דלא בני קרבן. Ma pesha'im dela bnei korban
af chata'im nami dela bnei korban. So אימא eima that's true, that
we have to identify a sin that doesn't have a קרבן korban
associated. אימא מה פשעים דלא בני קרבן לעולם אף חטאים דלא בני
קרבן לעולם. Eima ma pesha'im dela bnei korban le'olam af chata'im dela
bnei korban le'olam. Maybe I should find something that would never have
the possibility of a קרבן, korban, just like a willful sin. ומאי
ניהו אין בה ידיעה בתחילה ויש בה ידיעה בסוף, Umai nihu ein
bah yedi'ah batchilah ve'yeish bah yedi'ah basof, meaning why pick this row?
Why not go to this case? If there's no ידיעה, yedi'ah, this
case where there's ידיעה yedi'ah, בתחילה not בסוף, basof, there's a possibility
of a קרבן korban once you become aware, right? So why did
we choose to say that it was this one? If the idea
is to find some type of a sin that קרבן korban is
not relevant for, then we should have picked this, because in this
case you'll never bring a קרבן. korban. Since you were lacking the
initial ידיעה, yediya you would never bring a קרבן korban for this
case. So why if we're saying יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones for
an unintentional sin of טומאת מקדש tumot mikdash that there's no קרבן
korban for, why did we pick this, right? Which is the one
that there's no קרבן korban just yet, but there could be a
קרבן korban once you become aware? Why don't we pick this one,
right? Or this one? Alright, where there will never be a קרבן.
korban. So the גמרא Gemara says ומאי ניהו אין בה ידיעה
בתחילה ויש בה ידיעה בסוף, Umai nihu ein bah yedi'ah batchilah ve'yeish
bah yedi'ah basof, but
let me say that something that there was a knowledge at the
beginning and not at the end. כיון דכי מתידע ליה בר קרבן
הוא, Keivan dechi mityada lei bar korban hu, since when you do
become aware you will bring a קרבן, korban, אימא לא לכפרי, eima
lo lachapperei, maybe it shouldn't suspend the punishment, maybe it shouldn't be
effective, right? If you really want something that's like a willful sin
that there's no קרבן, korban, you should pick this or this. This
at least has a קרבן korban in the end. Why are we
picking this one? Okay? וכי תימא אין בה ידיעה בתחילה ויש בה
ידיעה בסוף שעיר הנעשה בחוץ ויום הכיפורים מכפר, Vechi teima ein bah
yedi'ah batchilah ve'yeish bah yedi'ah basof sa'ir hane'aseh bachutz ve'Yom Hakippurim mechapper,
oh but
no, no, no, I know it can't be this. You know how
I know
it can't be this? This one, because this one already you've got
the מוסף Musaf for. But that's not an answer. The only because
I'm figuring out this chart right now, right? Don't say, oh, the
reason we didn't have
the inner קרבן korban of יום כיפור Yom Kippur work on say
that it applied here was this is already assigned the מוסף Musaf
of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. That's not an answer. We're trying to
figure it out. Why don't we switch it? Why don't we say
this one gets the inner קרבן korban and this one gets the
מוסף Musaf קרבן? korban? Okay? So the גמרא says סלקא דעתך אמינא
נהפוך מיפך, Salka da'atach amina nahapoch mippach,
let's just reverse it. Okay? So you can't say oh we've already
have that doing something. How do you know you have it doing
something? Alright, so that's the question. Yes, it can't be this, it
has to be something that there's no קרבן. korban. All these three
have no
קרבן. korban. What made you pick this scenario where there'll be a
קרבן korban at the end? So אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse
says לכל חטאתם, lechol chatotam מכלל דבני חטאת נינהו. miklal debnei chatat
ninhu.
So פשעיהם pisheihem tells you not this. Okay? פשעיהם Pisheihem tells you
it cannot be this one because this one has a קרבן. korban.
But לכל חטאתם lechol chatotam tells me, yes, no קרבן korban now,
that's what פשעיהם pisheihem says, no קרבן korban now, just like
an intentional sin. Wait, wait, let me just finish this point. פשעיהם
Pisheihem tells me there's no קרבן korban now, so it's one of
these three. That we get from פשעיהם. pisheihem. But לכל חטאתם lechol
chatotam tells me it will become, lead into a חטאת, chatat something
that has the possibility of a חטאת chatat. eventually. So it's the
combination of the two. פשעיהם Pisheihem tells me something that is not
a קרבן, korban, that is not obligated in a קרבן korban right
now, which excludes this. לכל חטאתם lechol chatotam tells me something that
could eventually turn into a חטאת. chatat So the only thing on
this chart that has no חטאת chatat now but could become a
חטאת chatat is this one. This one has no חטאת chatat now
because you're not aware yet, but it could become a חטאת chatat
when you become aware. This one is a חטאת chatat. now, and
this one will never have a חטאת. Okay? So the לכל חטאתם
tells me this will be atoned for something that there is no
קרבן korban that you're obligated in right now, the individual, because he's
not aware, but that he could become obligated in when he becomes
aware. And that's how we learn out that it applies to this
scenario. Yes.
What if we continue the chart like תחילת וסוף... techilat ve'sof... Suppose
we continue the chart, like let's do תחילה וסוף *techila v'sof* to
put מפי שמועה *mipi shemu'ah* one column and then לכל חטאתם *l'chol
chatosam* and then we can mark which one applies.
Oh, I see what you're saying.
All right, you want to do it like that. That's interesting. I
really need another column. Okay, but מפי שמועה *mipi shemu'ah*
and לכל חטאתם *l'chol chatosam*. So מפי שמועה *mipi shemu'ah*, I hear
your point. מפי שמועה *mipi
shemu'ah*
and לכל חטאתם *l'chol
chatosam*. So
what you're saying is that מפי שמועה *mipi shemu'ah*, which means that
no קרבן korban *korban*,
right? So this isn't מפי שמועה *mipi shemu'ah*, so all these three
are possibilities. So the גמרא *Gemara* was considering all those three possibilities.
But לכל חטאתם *l'chol chatosam* means
eventually a חטאת *chatas*, which is not this and not this, and
the only thing you're left with is that. Okay, yeah, okay, very
good. All right, anyway, this is the one we focus in on.
No קרבן korban *korban* now, there will be a קרבן korban. *korban*
eventually. Okay, וניכפר כפרה גמורה *v'nichpar kapara gemura*,
so why don't we say that if it's applying to this case,
why don't we say that it is after- sorry, I just need
space now that we got that. Okay, it's too many checks and
Xs anyway. Now that it's applying to this case, why don't we
say- why do we say it's only תולה *toleh*, it only suspends,
meaning it somehow atones until you become aware. And but when you
become aware you do have to bring a חטאת *chatas*. The whole
לכל חטאתם *l'chol chatosam* says you will bring a חטאת *chatas* if
eventually you could eventually bring a חטאת *chatas*. Why don't we say
that after יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* you're totally off the hook? יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur* not just suspended but atoned. And even if you
become aware after, maybe you don't have to bring a קרבן korban.
*korban*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, וניכפר כפרה גמורה *v'nichpar kapara gemura*,
let it totally atone, so you wouldn't have to bring a קרבן
korban. *korban* even if you became aware. אי כתיב מחטאתם *Ei ketiv
meichatosam*,
it atones from the sin, that means that it cleanses the sin,
כדקאמרת *kidka'amart*, you'd be right, and then you wouldn't have to bring
a קרבן korban *korban* if you became aware after יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*. השתא דכתיב לכל חטאתם *Hashta deketiv l'chol chatosam*, for the חטאת
*chat*, והא חטאת לכל חטאת *veha chatas l'chol chatas*. Again, it means
something that eventually the חטאת *chatas* is still, it doesn't cleanse you
from the sin, it doesn't remove the sin. It atones for the
purpose of the sin, but it means ultimately ל- *le-* like towards
a חטאת *chatas* that eventually a
חטאת *chatas* is still in the offing, remains in the offing. And
if you become aware you will have to bring a חטאת *chatas*.
Now the גמרא *Gemara* says, וכי מאחר שאינו מכפר למה תולה *vechi
mei'achar she'eino mechaper lama toleh*? If it's not going to atone, who
needs it to do anything? What's it doing? I'll still have to
bring a חטאת *chatas* if I become aware. It's not cleansing. What's
it doing for me? What's תולה *toleh* mean, suspend? What are you
suspending?
So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר רבי זירא לומר שאם מת מת
בלא עוון *Amar Rabi Zeira lomar she'im mes mes belo avon*. Now,
here's what it does. Let's say you die without ever realizing that
you sinned. So let's say you never wind up bringing that sin
offering. This thing will atone for you. This atones for you as
long as you do not become aware that you have sinned and
then you require a new atonement. But if you remain oblivious your
whole life, then this thing atones. That's a reasonable thing to say.
So אמר ליה רבא *amar lei Rava*, so רבא *Rava* says, אם
מת מיתה ממרקת *im mes misa memarekes*. No,
if you die, yes, you'll be atoned for, but why would we
assume you need this to do anything? Your death will cleanse you
from the sin. So what do we- if this isn't really going
to get me out of bringing my חטאת *chatas* and if I
died and I was oblivious my death would atone, what is this
doing for me? אלא אמר רבא להגן עליו מן היסורין *Ela amar
Rava lehagein alav min hayisurin*. What it means is that yes, your
death will atone for you, but if you never did anything to
address this sin, you might have to suffer in life for this
thing that you're unaware of. And this קרבן korban. *korban* is protecting
you from that suffering that you would have to deal with. So
this is a very heavy idea, right? If you think about it,
here's this guy, he did a sin, he was unintentional, he was
שוגג *shogeg*, he's not even aware that he sinned yet, he's going
around oblivious. Okay, it doesn't mean he was blameless, he could have
been more careful, and that's what שוגג *shogeg* is, that you weren't
as careful as you could be. But he did this one sin,
he's going around oblivious, and somehow he might suffer in life through
divinely ordained suffering and punishment for the sin that he did and
being oblivious to it and that he did בשוגג *beshogeg*, right? That's
quite whoa. Okay, so you're wondering why you're having it so bad,
you know, this is like, oh, well it's because of this one
sin you did and you were totally oblivious about and you did
it בשוגג *beshogeg*. It's like that is a very heavy
theology. But now we find, but that's why you're bringing a קרבן
korban *korban* on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* to protect you from those
types of sufferings. Of course, that would be nice if I would
say the קרבן korban. *korban* would do that for all sins, all
sins I do before I'm aware of, you know, this should like
protect
me. I know, I know. Exactly. I mean, that's why, in the
וידוי Viddui we say,
על הודע ולא הודע, al hoda ve-lo hoda, the things that we're
aware of, the things like there's things we're not aware of. So
we can do like a generic תשובה teshuva for them, right?
But it says,
הנסתרות, HaNistarot, actually interesting, right? Because actually at the end of the
וידוי Viddui on יום כפור Yom Kippur we say, הנסתרות, HaNistarot, הנסתרות
לה׳ אלוקינו, HaNistarot L'Hashem Elokeinu, אלוקינו, Elokeinu, whatever, קינו, keinu, והנגלות
לנו ולבנינו.
ve-ha-niglot lanu
u-le-vaneinu.
Now
normally, לנו ולבנינו, lanu u-le-vaneinu, God knows the hidden things,
for us is the revealed things. So normally the פשט pshat of
that פסוק means I don't have, I'm not accountable for your sin,
it's hidden from me, I'm only accountable, the public is only accountable,
the community is only accountable for what it sees
publicly. That's what נגלה nigla versus נסתרות nistarot means. But in the
context of the וידוי Viddui on יום כפור, Yom Kippur, what this
means is that I actually cannot be accountable for things for myself
for things that I'm not aware of. This quoting of this פסוק
in the וידוי Viddui יום כפור Yom Kippur is exactly directly addressing
this scenario
about God; at the end of the day, you can't hold me
accountable for something I don't even know that I did. The things
that are hidden, whatever, that's not my responsibility,
God, or you can't hold me accountable. So it's actually quite interesting
if you think about how this plays out,
we say על הודע ולא הודע, al hoda ve-lo hoda, we sort
of do all of that in the וידוי of יום כפור, Yom
Kippur, but then we quote this פסוק to really say you really
can't hold me so accountable for those things. And here we're saying
that that's the entire purpose of this קרבן is to protect you
for something that you're oblivious of. Okay, so let's now read a
little bit further.
All right, so that was that. אין בידיעה בתחילה ויש בידיעה בסוף
שעיר הנעשה בחוץ ויום הכיפורים מכפר. ein bayediya bitchila veyesh bayediya besof
seir naaseh bachutz ve-Yom Kippurim mechaper. Now we've moved on, so this
one
is מטומאת בני ישראל, mitumat bnei Yisrael, מטום, mitum, מטום, mitum, whatever,
טומאת בני ישראל tumat bnei Yisrael ומפשעיהם, u-mipisheihem, ומפשעיהם u-mipisheihem ולכל חטאתם.
u-le-chol chatotam.
Okay, and now that's this one. יש בידיעה בתחילה ואין בידיעה בסוף.
yesh bayediya bitchila ve'ein bayediya besof. Now, how do we know the
מוסף Musaf is מכפר for the flip case? אין בידיעה בתחילה ויש
בידיעה בסוף. ein bayediya bitchila veyesh bayediya besof. So remember, we're going
back to the actual משנה. mishna. The first משנה mishna says the
way we know that is because it says מלבד חטאת הכפורים. milvad
chatat hakippurim.
מלבד חטאת הכפורים. milvad chatat hakippurim. That's what it says by the
מוסף. Musaf. And it says על מה שזה מכפר על מה שזה
מכפר
זה מכפר.
al ma shezeh mechaper al ma shezeh
mechaper zeh mechaper. The link of the two said this
functions like this. Okay, now it's not exactly, because this is on
this case and this is on this case, but it means it's
טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash and יש בידיעה. yesh bayediya. It's just the
flip. But the comparison is telling you this is טומאת מקדש tumat
mikdash and יש בידיעה, yesh bayediya, this is טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash
and יש בידיעה, yesh bayediya, okay? But the ידיעה occurs in a
different place. That's what the משנה mishna says. And that's how you
know that this atones for when you're aware to begin, when you're
not aware to beginning and you are aware at the end. So
let's continue in the גמרא. מכדי, meichti, איתקושי איתקוש אהדדי. iskushei iskishu
ahadadi.
If they're really linked to one another, וליכפר פנימי אדידיה ואדיד חיצון.
venechaper pnimi adidei ve-adei chitzon. Why don't we say, if they're really
linked, then this one works for both cases, the one we said
and what the outer קרבן works for? Maybe it works for both
of the scenarios since they're linked to one another. דנפקא מינה, denafka
mina, why do you need it to do both? I mean, why
isn't it enough that one does one per sin? להיכא דלא עביד
חיצון. leheicha delo avid chitzon.
Maybe if for some reason you ran out
of the necessary animals and you couldn't do the one, maybe because
they're linked, it's telling you don't worry, the one on the inside
worked for both.
So אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says אחת. achat. It says
וכפר אהרן על קרנתיו אחת בשנה. ve-chiper Aharon al karnotav achat bashana.
He does it once in the year. That's what it says by
the inner קרבן. כפרה אחת מכפר ואינו מכפר שתי כפרות. kapara achat
mechaper ve-eino mechaper shtei kaparot.
The word אחת achat that appears by here says it only does
its own job. It doesn't do two acts of atonement. So yes,
they're linked, they're linked enough to tell you they're similar, but they're
also distinct. אחת achat says this is only doing its atonement, it's
not doing the atonement of another קרבן. So the גמרא says all
right, but now let's ask the question in reverse. וליכפר חיצון אדידיה
ואמאי דעביד פנימי. venechaper chitzon adidei ve-amai de-avid pnimi.
As long as they're linked, this might say אחת. achat. So this
says it's only doing one thing. But how about this one? Let
this one do its role and because they're linked it'll also do
the atonement of the inner קרבן. All right, it only says אחת.
achat. Out of here, this one does one atonement. Let this one
do two atonements because they're linked. Yeah, everybody's getting this? Okay. ומכפר
חיצון עדידיה ומאי דעביד פנימי, u'mechaper chitzon adideih u'mai d'avid pnimi, נפקא
מינה לטומאה דאירע בין זה לזה, nafka mina l'tumah d'ira bein zeh
l'zeh,
and the relevance would be if let's say somebody became טמא after
the inner קרבן was brought before the מוסף Musaf קרבן. So then
the מוסף Musaf is like a backup, it's a belt and suspenders.
Oh, if something happened between these two, don't worry, the מוסף Musaf
does its own job and it does the job of the inner
one. Why don't we say that? אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse
says אחת בשנה. achat bashanah. It says again אחת. achat. רש"י Rashi
says it says אחת achat twice. It says וכיפר אהרן על קרנותיו
אחת בשנה ve'chiper Aharon al karnotav achat bashanah and then the פסוק
goes on and it says what it says וכיפר אהרן על קרנותיו
אחת בשנה מדם חטאת הכיפורים אחת בשנה יכפר. ve'chiper Aharon al karnotav
achat bashanah midam chatat hakipurim achat bashanah yechaper. Okay, so it says
אחת בשנה achat bashanah twice. כפרה זו לא תהא אלא אחת בשנה.
kaparah zo lo tehei ela achat bashanah.
So the אחת בשנה achat bashanah is telling you this, this atonement
up here is only done once. So the אחת achat says this
קרבן only does one thing and the אחת בשנה achat bashanah says
this atonement here is only is only taken care of once. So
this only does one thing, it does not do the work down
here. This atonement is only taken care of once, so it's not
taken care of by another קרבן. Okay, so the two אחת achat
are basically telling you, yes, they're linked to tell you they're both
טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash and they're both יש בידיעה, yesh biyedia, but
they also remain distinct. This does the case of knowing in the
beginning and not knowing at the end and this does the case
of not knowing at the end, excuse me, did I get that
right? Not knowing, this one takes the case of knowing at the
beginning and not at the end and this takes care of the
case of not knowing at the beginning and knowing at the end.
So they're obviously very similar, they're linked, but they remain distinct as
well. And that's how we know now those two and we're just
left with like the last one, okay? So we will continue with
this tomorrow.